Sahil Garg

Data Scientist

<u>garg6458@gmail.com</u>

J +91-7889146301

in LinkedIn

GitHub

Sangrur, Punjab

Summary:

Strong programming experience in Python and Individual with over 5 months of experience in building or training Machine Learning and Deep Learning models and turning Data Science prototypes into production-grade solutions. One who is also familiar with collecting, cleaning and organizing data for use by technical and non-technical personnel.

Skills:

• Technical Skills:

Python	Machine Learning	Deep Learning	Data Science	Natural Language Processing
Computer Vision	Data Visualization	Data Scraping	Feature Engineering	Exploratory Data Analysis
SQL	MySQL	NumPy	Pandas	Matplotlib
Scikit-Learn	TensorFlow	Keras	NLTK	SciPy
Regex	Transformers	OpenCV	BeautifulSoup	Selenium

• Personal Skills:

Communication Team Work Leadership Presentation Collaboration

Work Experience:

Software Engineer (ML\NLP) Intern

September 2021 – Present

Scintillation Research and Analytics Services

Mohali, Punjab

Project: Prior Art Search & SEPs **Domain:** Intellectual Property (IP)

Description: Building a software (Agile) that performs Patent-to-Patent, Patent-to-Standard and Patent-to-

Product searches to minimize human intervention.

Contributions:

- R & D at least 3 to 4 possible ways to solve specific problems and choose the best.
- Built a dictionary with the key-value pairs that represents words to list of synonyms for 17,000 words.
- Developed a module which can perform Patent-to-Standard search; reduced cost of labour by 75%.

Data Science Intern

May 2021 - August 2021

Mvg Innovations

Hyderabad, Telangana

- Headed the team of 5 Data Scientist Interns for 2 months and increased the throughput by 20%.
- Interviewed 20+ candidates for the Data Science Intern role.
- Supervised the whole organization including cross-functional departments for 1 month; conducted daily morning meetings and on-boarding meetings.
- Trained an intent classification model and a module to extract all the useful information for chat bot queries with the accuracy of 92%.
- Scraped replies of politicians' tweets and performed sentimental analysis with 81+ macro average.
- Built personalized and non-personalized (popularity based) recommendation system to recommend combined prediction of both models for million rows data size.

Projects:

Facial Recognition

GitHub

- Used 4-5 images of every person with different angles to store their facial encodings in list and found the
 encodings of all the faces in the test image and then comparing these encodings to give a bounding box around
 the faces.
- Attendance System using Facial Recognition: Used the same above technique to have encodings and whenever they are in the range of the camera and get detected, their name and detection time will be saved in the Attendance.csv file.

Fake News Detector GitHub

Trained a fake news detector using Logistic Regression on the political news from the US with the F1-Score of 99.29 on test data.

Mini Proiects GitHub

• Created a function to take scale and list of images as input and return the stacked image of the images irrespective of the dimensions and shape.

 Created a module when input image returns warped image of the user initialized points, one just needs to select 4 points using mouse while displaying the image, and continue to get the next warped image.

Sentimental Analysis

Git Hub

- Performed sentimental analysis on Drug Review Dataset with over 200,000 patient drug reviews.
- Developed a model for sentiment analysis with 14337 Amazon reviews and star rating from 1 to 5.

Education:

Bachelors of Information Technology (BIT) – CGPA: 7.4 (till 4th Sem)

Aug 2018 - Sep 2021

Alpine Institute of Management and Technology

Dehradun, Uttarakhand

Higher Secondary Certificate – PCM: 93.3%

March 2017 - May 2018

Senior Secondary Certificate - CGPA: 10

March 2015 - April 2016

FCS Adarsh Sr. Sec. School

Sangrur, Punjab

Achievements:

Academic:

- Participated in Hackathon 3.0 held at University of Petroleum and Energy Studies in February, 2019.
- Earned the LinkedIn Skill badge in Python & Machine Learning and took the top 15% and top 10%, respectively.
- Merit in National Financial Literacy Assessment Test, 2014.
- Letter of Recommendation from Mvg Innovations.

Extra-Curricular:

- Addressed a gathering of 2000+ people twice.
- Anchored two college events in front of more than 3000 people.